313-2022 Main Mall, Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z4, Canada

p.pata@oceans.ubc.ca | +1 236 979 7282 https://github.com/PatrickPata

### **PROFILE**

I am a biological oceanographer focused on zooplankton ecology. I am interested in understanding the oceanographic and ecological drivers of zooplankton distributions and how the emergent spatiotemporal trends translate into ecosystem functions and services. Most of my work involve the synthesis of observations of water properties, plankton communities, and species-specific traits. My research is aimed towards supporting the development of mechanistic ecosystem models and promoting the consideration of the role of zooplankton in informing ocean conservation and management.

### **DEGREES**

2019 – 2024	Doctor of Philosophy in Oceanography Department of Earth, Ocean, and Atmospheric Sciences, University of British Columbia Thesis: Structure and functioning of zooplankton communities of the Canadian Northeast Pacific Ocean.	
2014 – 2017	Master of Science in Marine Science  Marine Science Institute, University of the Philippines  Thesis: Philippine coral reef connectivity and network analysis.	
2008 – 2012	Bachelor of Science in Psychology, magna cum laude College of Social Science and Philosophy, University of the Philippines	
	WORK EXPERIENCE	
June 2024 – present	Postdoctoral Research Fellow - Pelagic Ecosystems Laboratory Institute for the Oceans and Fisheries, University of British Columbia, Canada	
May 2019 – May 2024	PhD Candidate - Pelagic Ecosystems Laboratory Institute for the Oceans and Fisheries, University of British Columbia, Canada	
Jan 2016 – Dec 2018	Masters Scholar - Capturing Coral Reef and Related Ecosystem Services Project Marine Science Institute, University of the Philippines Diliman, Philippines	
Jul 2012 – Dec 2015	Research Assistant - Biological Oceanography and Modelling of Ecosystems Lab Marine Science Institute, University of the Philippines Diliman, Philippines	
AWARDS AND GRANTS		
<i>2024</i> Pa	ul J. Harrison Memorial Award in Oceanography, University of British Columbia, 2,800 CAD	
<ul> <li>Zooplankton Production Symposium Travel Grant, 1,400 CAD</li> <li>Department of Earth, Ocean and Atmospheric Sciences Graduate Scholarship, University of British Columbia, 1,500 CAD</li> <li>Association for the Sciences of Limnology and Oceanography Student Travel Grant, 800 USD</li> </ul>		
	nadian Institute of Ecology and Evolution – Living Data Project grant for organizing a working group, 13,800 CAD H. Mathews Scholarship, University of British Columbia, 5,000 CAD	
Pa	ERC Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship-Doctoral, 105,000 CAD ul J. Harrison Memorial Award in Oceanography, University of British Columbia, 4,300 CAD ernational Biogeography Society Student Travel Award, 500 USD	
<i>2020</i> Fo	ur year Dectoral Fallowship, University of British Columbia, 19,200 CAD	
2020 F0	ur-year Doctoral Fellowship, University of British Columbia, 18,200 CAD	

313-2022 Main Mall, Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z4, Canada

p.pata@oceans.ubc.ca | +1 236 979 7282 https://github.com/PatrickPata

### PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- **Pata, P.R.**, Galbraith, M., Young, K., Margolin, A., Perry, R.I., and Hunt, B.P.V. (2024). Data-driven determination of zooplankton bioregions and robustness analysis. *MethodsX*, 12, 102676.
- **Pata, P.R.**, and Hunt, B.P.V. (2023). Harmonizing marine zooplankton trait data towards a mechanistic understanding of ecosystem functioning. *Limnology and Oceanography*. (Early view)
- **Pata, P.R.**, Galbraith, M., Young, K., Margolin, A., Perry, R.I., and Hunt, B.P.V. (2022). Persistent zooplankton bioregions reflect long-term consistency of community composition and oceanographic drivers in the NE Pacific. *Progress in Oceanography*, 206, 102849.
- Currie, J., Blain, S.A., Emry, S., Hebert, K., Xie, G., Moore, N., Wang, X., Brown, A., Burant, J.B., Grevstad, L., Marconi, V., McRae, L., Mezzini, S., **Pata, P.R.**, and Freeman, R. (2022). Assessing the representation of species included within the Canadian Living Planet Index. *FACETS*, 7: 1121–1141.
- **Pata, P.R.**, Yñiguez A.T. (2021). Spatial planning insights for Philippine coral reef conservation using larval connectivity networks. *Frontiers in Marine Science*, 1406.
- **Pata, P.R.**, Yñiguez A.T., Deauna, J.D., De Guzman, A.B., Jimenez, C.R., Borja-del Rosario, R., and Villanoy, C. (2021). Insights into the environmental conditions contributing to variability in the larval recruitment of the tropical sardine *Sardinella lemuru*. *Ecological Modelling*, 451, 109570.
- Cabasan, J.P., Arceo, H.O., **Pata, P.R.**, Labrador, K.L., Casauay, R.B., Miller, N., Rodriguez, M.V.B. (2021). Combining information on otolith morphometrics and larval connectivity models to infer stock structure of *Plectropomus leopardus* in the Philippines. *Marine Ecology Progress Series*, 679, 115-131.
- **Pata, P.R.**, Yñiguez A.T. (2019). Larval connectivity patterns of the North Indo-West Pacific coral reefs. *PLoS ONE* 14(7): e0219913.

## **TECHNOLOGY TRANSFER**

Horigue, V., Balingit A.C., **Pata P.R.**, Villanoy, C.L., Quibilan, M.C., Licuanan, W.Y., and Aliño, P.M. (2018) Fish SPACE: a spatial tool for marine reserve design and fisheries management [Computer Software]. Capturing Coral Reefs and Related Ecosystems Project (CCRES). Quezon City, Philippines.

### **JOURNAL PEER REVIEW**

2024	Regional Studies in Marine Science (Elsevier)
2023	Bulletin of Marine Science (Rosenstiel School of Marine, Atmospheric, and Earth Science)
2023	Coral Reefs (Springer)
2022	Marine Pollution Bulletin (Elsevier)

### **EXPERIENCE AT SEA**

Aug 11, 2022 & May 18, 2023	Howe Sound, British Columbia small-vessel field sampling Institute for the Oceans and Fisheries, University of British Columbia
Jul 4 – 14, 2022	Quadra Island and Bute Inlet, British Columbia small-vessel field sampling Institute for the Oceans and Fisheries, University of British Columbia
Mar 2 – 10, 2014, Feb 18 – 26, 2013	Bohol Sea – Zamboanga Upwelling Cruise aboard MV <i>DA-BFAR</i> Marine Science Institute, University of the Philippines Diliman
May 7 – 16, 2013	Luzon Strait Cruise aboard R/V Roger Revelle Scripps Institute of Oceanography, University of California, San Diego
2012 – 2016	Various small-vessel field work at different areas of the Philippines

313-2022 Main Mall, Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z4, Canada

p.pata@oceans.ubc.ca | +1 236 979 7282 https://github.com/PatrickPata

## **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

- Computer programming in R, Matlab, Java, and Python
- Numerical ecology analysis, particularly multivariate statistics
- Analysis of satellite and physical oceanography data
- Oceanographic data collection and laboratory processing
- Individual-based modelling
- Species distribution modelling
- Ordinary differential equation modelling
- GIS and spatial decision-support tools with QGIS and Marxan
- Ocean circulation modelling with HYCOM and Delft3d
- Administering workshops, stakeholder interviews, and focused group discussions
- CMAS 1-Star Open Water SCUBA diver
- Developing psychometric scales and social science questionnaires
- Scientific illustration and graphic design

### **WORKING GROUPS AND ACADEMIC TRAININGS**

Mar 2024	Workshop co-organizer for: Approaches towards findable, accessible, interoperable and reusable (FAIR) zooplankton trait data as stepping stones to improved functional ecology. 7th ICES-PICES Zooplankton Production Symposium, Tasmania.
Feb 2024	Instructional Skills Workshop. Center for Teaching, Learning, and Technology. University of British Columbia.
Feb 2023	Living Data Project working group: Linking species distributions and traits to understand ecosystem functioning. Vancouver, Canada.
Apr 2022	Certificate in Synthetic and Collaborative Science – Canadian Institute of Ecology and Evolution (CIEE).
Aug – Sep 2021	Living Data Project working group: Finding indicator species by assessing the utility of sampled abundance indices. Online.
Oct – Nov 2019	Foundations of Pedagogy Course. Center for Teaching, Learning, and Technology. University of British Columbia.
Jun 2019	WestGrid Research Computing Summer School. University of British Columbia.
Aug – Sep 2016	South-East Asia Network for Education and Training (SEA-NET) Project. Summer intern under Prof. Sen Jan, Institute of Oceanography, National Taiwan University, Taiwan.
Oct 2014	Training in ASEAN Oceanography, Marine and Coastal Resources Network Conference, Phuket, Thailand.
2014 – 2024	13 international and regional conference presentations. 3 invited speaker talks.

313-2022 Main Mall, Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z4, Canada

p.pata@oceans.ubc.ca | +1 236 979 7282 https://github.com/PatrickPata

### **CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

- **Pata, P.R.,** Galbraith, M., Young, K., Sastri, A., Perry, R.I., and Hunt, B.P.V. (2024, March). *Extracting region-specific trait values of functional groups from a global zooplankton trait database.* 7<sup>th</sup> Zooplankton Production Symposium, Hobart, Tasmania.
- **Pata, P.R.** and Hunt, B.P.V. (2023, Sep). *Development and applications of a global harmonized zooplankton trait database*. FishBase Symposium, online.
- **Pata, P.R.** and Hunt, B.P.V. (2023, Jun). *Developing a global harmonized zooplankton trait database.*Association for the Sciences of Limnology and Oceanography 2023 Aquatic Sciences Meeting, Mallorca, Spain.
- **Pata, P.R.**, Burant J., Mezzini, S., Currie, J., McRae, L., Freeman, R., and Marconi, V. (2022, Aug). *A sampled approach to abundance biodiversity indicators.* Ecological Society of America Canadian Society for Ecology and Evolution Joint Meeting, Montreal, Canada.
- **Pata, P.R.**, Galbraith, M., Young, K., Margolin, A., Perry, R.I., and Hunt, B.P.V. (2022, Jun). *The persistent cross-shelf regionalization of zooplankton communities in coastal oceans*. Biennial conference of the International Biogeography Society, Vancouver, Canada.
- **Pata, P.R.**, Galbraith, M., Young, K., Margolin, A., Perry, R.I., and Hunt, B.P.V. (2022, Mar). *Persistence of biogeographic regions across 20-years of zooplankton community observations in the NE Pacific.* Ocean Sciences Meeting, online.
- **Pata, P.R.**, Margolin, A., Galbraith, M., Young, K., Perry, I., and Hunt, B.P.V. (2020, Mar). *Zooplankton bioregionalization of the British Columbia coastal ocean.* State of the Pacific Ocean Meeting, Nanaimo, Canada.
- Pata, P.R., Galbraith, M., Young, K., Perry, I., and Hunt, B.P.V. (2019, Oct). Sensitivity analysis on zooplankton bioregionalization of British Columbia. North Pacific Marine Science Organization (PICES) Annual Meeting, Victoria, Canada. (Best Poster Award)
- Pata, P.R. and Yñiguez A.T. (2017, Jul) *Insights on national coral reef conservation from a regional connectivity network analysis.* 14<sup>th</sup> National Symposium of the Philippine Association of Marine Science, Batangas, Philippines. (Best Poster Award)
- **Pata, P.R.** and Yñiguez A.T. (2015, Oct) *A settlement competency approach to national scale reef connectivity*. Philippine 13<sup>th</sup> National Symposium of the Association of Marine Science. General Santos City, Philippines.
- **Pata, P.R.** and Yñiguez A.T. (2014, Oct) *Ecosystem modelling of Sardinella lemuru in the Southern Philippines*. 46<sup>th</sup> Annual National Convention of the Federation of Institutions for Marine and Freshwater Sciences. Dapitan City, Philippines.
- **Pata, P.R.**, Deauna, J.D., Borja-del Rosario, R., Yñiguez A.T., and Villanoy, C. (2014, Jul) *Emergent* spatiotemporal distribution patterns of an individual-based biophysical model of early life stage sardines (Sardinella lemuru) in the southern Philippines. 11<sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting of the Asia Oceania Geosciences Society, Sapporo, Japan.
- **Pata, P.R.**, Yñiguez A.T., Villanoy, C., Deauna, J.D., and Borja-del Rosario, R. (2014, Apr) *An individual-based model of Sardinella lemuru as a potential management tool in the southern Philippines*. 9<sup>th</sup> International Scientific Symposium of the IOC Sub-Commission for the Western Pacific (WESTPAC), Nha Trang, Vietnam.

313-2022 Main Mall, Vancouver, BC V6T 1Z4, Canada

p.pata@oceans.ubc.ca | +1 236 979 7282 https://github.com/PatrickPata

## TEACHING, MENTORSHIP, AND OUTREACH

- Working group leader for the Living Data Project working group with graduate students and postdocs on Linking species distributions and traits to understand ecosystem functioning.
- Teaching assistant for the University of British Columbia courses on Biological Oceanography (1 term, 2023), Methods in Oceanography (2 terms, 2020 & 2021), The Ocean Ecosystem (1 term, 2020), and The Catastrophic Earth (1 term, 2019).
- Mentor of the University of British Columbia undergraduate projects of A. Reinhardt (2021) on The relationship between pelagic larval duration and latitudinal range shifts of coastal invertebrates, and Y. Wu (2022) on Using Benford's Law to assess biodiversity datasets.
- Mentor of University of British Columbia masters student J. Fast (2021 present) who has a project on zooplankton nutritional quality.
- Facilitator and module designer for the Department of Science and Technology Science Education Institute, Philippines, Marine Science Summer Camps (2013 – 2015).
- I illustrated over 30 art pieces of zooplankton diversity shared in Instagram as #zoopoftheweek. I also created a public repository of zooplankton line art.
- I collaborated with musicians in the Earth Tones project (2023) and created a clarinet quartet piece about temporal trends in ecological cycles which is titled *Match-Mismatch*.
- From 2009 to 2012, I was a member of organizations that organize coastal cleanups in the Philippines through trash collection in shorelines and coral reefs.
- In 2008, I lead a high school club in a public health project which addressed gastrointestinal worm infections. We were recognized as one of the Ten Accomplished Youth Organizations of the Philippines.